

# Charlotte Guertler, PhD

Mechanical Engineer Aerospace and Biomechanics

charlotteguertler.github.io

id

orcid: 0000-0003-0605-0239

1

LinkedIn: Charlotte Guertler



charlotte.guertler@gmail.com

### About me ———

Charlotte is a mechanical engineer specializing in biomechanics and aerospace. She has experience in finite element analysis, mechanics, imaging, design, 3D bioprinting, material characterization, and project management. She is currently a mechanical engineering analysit at L3Harris. Previously, Charlotte was a Senior Scientist in brain biomechanics research and the associate director of the engineering design makerspace at Washington University and consulted for a neuroscience startup. Charlotte is excited to leverage her extensive analysis, research, design, and fabrication experience in R&D engineering.

### Skills ———

R&D

Finite element analysis, animal/human studies, MR imaging, MR elastography (MRE), focused ultrasound

**Engineering Software** 

Femap, COMSOL, SolidWorks, Autodesk Fusion 360, Tinkercad

Building, fabrication, prototyping 3D printing, laser cutting, machining & fabrication, welding, woodworking, sandblasting & powder coating, injection molding, vacuum forming

**Publishing Software** 

Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, CorelDRAW, Inkscape, LaTeX

## Education

2019 PhD Washington University in St. Louis

Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science Certificate in Imaging Science & Engineering

2017 MS Washington University in St. Louis

Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science

2014 BS Yale University

Mechanical Engineering, ABET accredited

### Research and Work Experience

2023-pres. Mechanical Engineering Analyst

L3Harris

Supervisor: Dave Calabrese and Kayla Mastovich

Finite element analysis of static, dynamic, and optical survival and per-

formance for the telescope of weather satelite pre-production.

2022 Engineering Consultant

RAPT Ventures, Inc.

Supervisor: Julia Whitehead

Product development of neuroscience-based infant language training

device.

2021-22 Senior Scientist

Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Demonstrate immediate changes in brain mechanical properties postmortem using MRE and create 3D bioprinted hydrogels with tunable anisotropy. Responsibilities: conduct research, supervise PhD, masters, and undergraduates, manage projects, write publications and proposals

2021-22 Engineering Consultant

DeepSight Technology

Supervisor: John Chong

Design, prototype, and fabricate novel ultrasound phantoms, demos,

and experimental setups

2019-22 Associate Director

Spartan Light Metal Products Makerspace

Supervisor: Dr. Ruth J. Okamoto

Design and manage curriculum, vision, and operations for university-

wide makerspace

2019-21 Staff Research Scientist

Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Develop novel anisotropic analysis for MR imaging of harmonic ultrasound-induced motion (MR-HUM) using machine learning and FEA  $\,$ 

and show effects of aging on anisotropy in brain using MRE.

2015-19 Graduate Student Researcher

Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Demonstrate mechanical property differences between in vivo and ex vivo brain, develop novel imaging method: MR imaging of harmonic ultrasound-induced motion (MR-HUM), and investigate anisotropy us-

ing finite element analysis.

# References

Philip V Bayly, PhD

The Lee Hunter Distinguished Professor of Mechanical Engineering Chair, Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science Washington University in St. Louis pvb@wustl.edu; 314-935-6081

Dave Calabrese

Senior Systems Engineer, Optical Payload Engineering

**General Atomics** 

Previously: Mechanical Engineering Manager at L3Harris

calabrese.dave@gmail.com; 508-930-6318

## **Publications**

\* authors contributed equally 2024 Post-mortem changes of anisotropic mechanical properties in the porcine brain assessed by MR elastography Wang S, Eckstein KN, Guertler CA, Johnson CL, Okamoto RJ, McGarry MDJ, Bayly PV Brain Multiphysics | 10.1016/j.brain.2024.100091 2023 Mechanical stiffness and anisotropy measured by MRE during brain development in the minipig Wang S, Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Johnson CL McGarry MDJ, Bayly PV Neuroimage | 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2023.120234 Measurement of relative motion of the brain and skull in the mini-pig in-vivo 2023 Kailash KA, Guertler CA, Johnson CL, Okamoto RJ, Bayly PV Journal of Biomechanics | 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2023.111676 2023 Design and characterization of 3-D printed hydrogel lattices with anisotropic mechanical properties Yoon D, Ruding M, Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Bayly PV Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials | 10.1016/j.jmbbm.2023.105652 2022 Estimation of the mechanical properties of a transversely isotropic material from shear wave fields via artificial neural networks Hou Z\*, Guertler CA\*, Okamoto RJ, Chen H, Garbow JR, Kamilov US, Bayly PV Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials | 10.1016/j.jmbbm.2021.105046 2021 A heterogenous, time harmonic, nearly incompressible transverse isotropic finite element brain simulation for MR elastography McGarry M, Van Houten E, Guertler C, Okamoto R, Smith D, Sowinski D, Johnson C, Bayly P, Weaver J, Paulsen Physics in Medicine and Biology | 10.1088/1361-6560/ab9a84 2020 Estimation of anisotropic material properties of soft tissue by MRI of ultrasound-induced shear waves Guertler CA. Okamoto RJ. Ireland J. Pacia C. Garbow JR. Chen H. Bayly PV Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4046127 Multi-excitation MR elastography of the brain: wave propagation in anisotropic white matter 2020 Smith D. Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Romano A, Bayly PV, Johnson CL Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4046199 Mechanical properties of porcine brain tissue in vivo and ex vivo estimated by MR elastography 2018 Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Schmidt JL, Badachhape AA, Johnson CL, Bayly PV Journal of Biomechanics | 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2018.01.016 2017 Validation of single c-arm fluoroscopic technique for measuring in vivo abdominal wall deformation Kahan LG, Guertler C, Blatnik JA, Lake SP Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4037073 2015 Patterned compliance in robotic finger pads for versatile surface usage in dexterous manipulation Bullock IM, Guertler C, Dollar AM IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation | 10.1109/ICRA.2015.7139545

2013

Grasp frequency and usage in daily household and machine shop tasks Bullock IM, Zheng JZ, De La Rosa S, Guertler C, Dollar AM

IEEE Transactions on Haptics | 10.1109/TOH.2013.6

2012

Mushy-layer dynamics in micro and hyper gravity

O'Rourke JG, Riggs AJE, Guertler CA, Miller PW, Padhi CM, Popelka MM, Wells AJ, West AC, Zhong J, Wettlaufer

JS

Physics of fluids | 10.1063/1.4760256

# **Patents**

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

Method and System for Treating Hypotension. 2009

> Patent US20110098580 Mikhail M and Guertler C